Finding Aid for the Robert E. Cowan Collection of Early California Manuscripts LSC.2048
UCLA Library Special Collections
Robert E. Cowan collection of early California manuscripts
1551-1932
UCLA Library Special Collections
Cowan, Robert Ernest
LSC.2048
5 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
116 Gigabytes (5,278 Files, 163 Folders) Files transferred from 1 hard drive.
Collection consists of miscellaneous manuscripts pertaining to California history.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Part purchase, part gift of Robert Cowan, 1936.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942327493606533
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Fremont Ackerman correspondence, ca. 1888-1895
Alta California, ca. 1834-1914
Attorneys, court, and legal records, ca. 1841-1896
Mexico, ca. 1551-1855
Newspaper clippings & manuscripts, ca. 1844-1892
Northern California, ca. 1845-1932
Pacific Northwest, ca. 1845-1890
Property records, ca. 1847-1877.
Biographical History
Robert Ernest Cowan was born in Toronto, Canada in 1862. He arrived in San Francisco in 1870 and was best known for the publication of bibliographies and other works on early California history including: A bibliography of the history of California, 1510-1930, Bibliography of the Chinese question in the United States (with Boutwell Dunlap), and The Spanish press of California, 1833-1845. Robert Ernest Cowan collected a wide-array of materials on early California history that would later form the nucleus of the UCLA Department of Special Collections's holdings in Californiana. Cowan was a former student at UC Berkeley from 1882-84, a San Francisco bookseller from 1895-1920, and a librarian for William Andrews Clark, Jr., from 1919-1933. Robert Cowan married Marie Margaret Fleissner in 1894 and they had one child, Robert Granniss Cowan. Robert Ernest Cowan died in Los Angeles in May 1942.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of early California manuscripts collected by Robert Ernest Cowan. Researchers on 19th century California may be especially drawn to the collection's extensive legal documents, property records, San Francisco materials, and documents relating to Spanish-Mexican California. The collection is comprised of materials mainly written in English, with a fair amount of documents written in Spanish and a few items written in Chinese and French. A few of the more interesting items in this collection are two manuscripts from 16th century Mexico, a deposition written in Chinese that was submitted as an exhibit in a U.S. District Court case, account ledgers showing mercantile transactions involving Spanish-Mexican families, requests for reimbursements stemming from the Mexican-American War, and property transactions involving women. A majority of the collection has been digitized and is available for access. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Related Material
Robert Ernest Cowan Papers (Collection 232). Available at the UCLA Library Special Collections.
Manuscripts, Spanish -- Mexico.; California -- History -- Sources.; Cowan, Robert Ernest; Ackerman, Fremont -- Correspondence
- Fremont Ackerman correspondence, ca. 1888-1895
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1888 January 7 - 1890 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1890 January 5 - December 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1891 January 6 - February 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1892 August 15 - December 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1893 January 7 - December 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1894 February 10 - 1895 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Alta California, ca. 1834-1914
  - Alta California -- Settlement Instructions, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alvarado, Juan Bautista, 1842 June 21 - 1868 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Berreyesa, ca. 1840 May 1 - 1845 July 29 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Castro Family Papers -- 1 of 2, ca. 1909 March 23 - 1914 September 16 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Castro Family Papers -- 2 of 2, ca. 1836 May 24 - 1864 September 20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1849 April 7 - 1896 July 11 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "El Trovador", 1874 August 19 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Estudillo, ca. 1838 February 11 - 1860 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - La Cronica, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mexican-American War, 1846 July 26 - 1855 January 4 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, ca. 1841 October 28 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Peralta, 1876 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pico, 1845 September 26 - 1854 April 23 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Property Documents, ca. 1834 December 24 - 1866 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Vallejo, ca. 1839 January 17 - 1863 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Attorneys, court, and legal records, ca. 1841-1896
  - Brooks, Benjamin S. (Sherman), ca. 1841 - 1873 February 18 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clarke, Samuel J., ca. 1865 January 5 - 1887 March 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Alameda County, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Amador County, 1863 November 19 - 1867 November 29 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Court/Legal Records -- California Supreme Court, ca. 1851 January 10 - 1865 December (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Court/Legal Records -- California District Court, 1850 May 22 - 1865 November 23 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Foreign Jurisdictions, ca. 1856 November 24 - 28 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Fresno County, 1856 November 3 - 1862 October 11 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Miscellaneous, ca. 1846 October 1 - 1866 June 9 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Sacramento County, 1866 August 25 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Court/Legal Records -- San Bernardino County, 1896 January 21 - August 26 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Court/Legal Records -- San Diego County, 1869 August 25 - 1880 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Court/Legal Records -- San Francisco County, ca. 1850 - 1894 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Santa Clara County, ca. 1851 November 13 - 1858 January 9 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Sierra County, 1867 July 17 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Siskiyou County, ca. 1858 December 7 - 1861 October 26 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Court/Legal Records -- Yolo County, 1862 July 5 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Crockett, Joseph B., 1856 July 28 - 1865 December (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Freeman, Eugene M., ca. 1887 May 4 - 1888 August 16 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lynch, Edward P., ca. 1881 March 1 - 1888 March 22 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Martel, James L., 1848 October 17 - 1887 December 7 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Court/Legal Records -- California Supreme Court, ca. 1861 February 6 - 1863 February 16 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Mexico, ca. 1551-1855
  - "History of the Chichimeca Nation" -- 1 of 4, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "History of the Chichimeca Nation" -- 2 of 4, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "History of the Chichimeca Nation" -- 3 of 4, n.d (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "History of the Chichimeca Nation" -- 4 of 4, n.d (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Legal Document, ca. 1551 August 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Legal Document, 1591 September 8 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Signature Book, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sonora Colonization, 1855 February 15 - March 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Newspaper clippings & manuscripts, ca. 1844-1892
  - Daily Alta, ca. 1856 November (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Pfieffer, George, ca. 1855 December 20 - 1860 December 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1854 January - 1863 January 9 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Shaw, William J. T., ca. 1844 - 1892 September 6 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Northern California, ca. 1845-1932
  - Account Ledgers, 1850 November 21 - 1855 July 17 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Adams & Company Express, ca. 1851 December 4 - 1854 September 29 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Alcatraz, 1864 July 24 - 29 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Alvarado Water Company, 1861 November 11 - 1895 February 19 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Banking Transactions, 1850 April 2 - 1867 August 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Bear River Inn, 1852 January 26 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Cadiz, Joseph G., ca. 1882 May 25 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - California Academy of Sciences, ca. 1885 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - California State Land Office, ca. 1852 - 1876 March 14 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Callahan, D. E., 1855 July 27 - 1860 July 30 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Chilean Consulate, 1874 June 13 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Chinese, ca. 1849 June 7 - 1864 April 11 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Churches, ca. 1860 June 11 - 1861 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Cole, Dr. R. Beverly, ca. 1856 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Contra Costa Water Company, 1890 February 18; photographs (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, photographs (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1847 August 4 - 1848 April 10; photographs (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1850 September 7 - 1859 September 9; photographs (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1860 July 9 - 1868 October 19; photographs (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, ca. 1872 April 26 - 1879 August 6 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, ca. 1882 February 5 - 1889 May 10 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, ca. 1890 October 21 - 1932 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Davis, William Heath -- Account Ledgers, ca. 1846 - 1847 December (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Davis, illiam Heath -- Correspondence, 1845 October 1 - 1854 March 1 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Dexter, Henry Stanley, ca. 1851 March 12 - 1877 February 28 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Eastman, T. M., 1865 May 22 - 1866 April 5 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Edwards, Frank G., 1858 December 13 - 1869 August 12 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Field & Co. -- Nevada City, ca. 1851 March 22 - July 25 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - First National Gold Bank of San Francisco, ca. 1870 - 1871 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Fremont, John Charles, ca. 1857 January 1 - 1861 February 26 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Gillespie, Charles V., ca. 1856 March (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Insurance, 1860 January 19 - 1868 October 14 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Langley, Henry G., 1855 October 5 - December 7 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Latham, Milton S., 1852 May 20 - December 6 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Leese, Jacob Primer, ca. 1846 November 28 - 1849 June 25 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Legislature, ca. 1852 May 3 - 1858 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Marriage Documents, 1850 February 9 - 1870 May 21 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mechanics Institute, 1858 September 21 - 1879 January 8 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Military, ca. 1847 March 1 - 1880 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mining, ca. 1853 June 26 - 1888 February 7 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, ca. 1855 November 13 - 1892 February 18 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Myles, Dr. Henry R., 1860 July 9 - 1865 December 28 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Passenger Lists, ca. 1849 March 2 - 1885 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Pierce & Company, ca. 1856 June 3 - 1869 July 26 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Promissory Notes/Liens, 1850 January 19 - 1870 December 16 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Purchase Orders/Invoice Receipts, ca. 1847 August 10 - 1869 October 21 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Railroad Companies, ca. 1857 March 14 - 1887 August 25 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Rents, ca. 1853 November 11 - 1871 October 20 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Richardson S. S. [Samuel Stone], ca. 1853 June - 1868 March 23 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - San Francisco -- Municipal Records, ca. 1848 April 20 - 1883 March 17 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Schools, ca. 1853 September 1 - 1868 April 21 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Shipping and Trade Records, ca. 1849 February 5 - 1868 October 14 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Society of California Pioneers, 1868 July 1 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Society of California Volunteers, 1854 October 21 - 1890 October 28 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Spring Valley Water Co., 1863 November 4 - 1864 February 1 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Steamboats/Steamships, ca. 1851 July 22 - 1868 April 25 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Stocks, 1857 March 18 - 1871 September 4 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Tax Receipts and Records, ca. 1852 October - 1894 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Telegraph/Telephone, ca. 1861 March - 1882 September 16 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Tuolumne County, ca. 1850 June 3 - 1855 October 31 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Tuolumne Hydraulic Association, 1853 February 9 - October 5 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - U.S. Treasury -- San Francisco, ca. 1851 March 29 - 1869 September 14 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Water Companies, 1854 March 4 - 1860 June 1 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Williams, A. F. (A. J.), 1871 March 23 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Williams, Stephen Hedden, 1865 March 17 - March 18 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Wilson, Benjamin D., 1856 June 15 - 1886 November 13 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Chinese, 1870 June 22 (Box 10)
  - Shipping and Trade Records (Box 10)
- Pacific Northwest, ca. 1845-1890
  - British Columbia, 1858 July 24 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oregon Cavalry, 1864 July 19 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Oregon Central Railroad Company, ca. 1867 - 1869 September 7 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oregon -- Correspondence, ca. 1848 February 29 - 1867 July 30 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Oregon -- Court Records, ca. 1851 November 13 - 1867 March 29 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Oregon -- Miscellaneous, ca. 1851 July 4 - 1890 August 30 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Oregon -- Property Records, 1850 April 24 - 1865 May 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Oregon -- Territory Board (Jackson County), ca. 1856 June 5 - 1866 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Washington, ca. 1845 May 5 - 1880 May 18 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - British Columbia, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Oregon -- Court Records, ca. 1861 July 1 (Box 10)
  - Oregon -- Property Records, 1858 July 12 (Box 10)
- Property records, ca. 1847-1877.
  - Alameda County, 1872 December 20 - 1873 January 20 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Amador County, 1863 July 22 - August 28 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Calaveras County, ca. 1863 March 31 - 1867 January 5 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Contra Costa County, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Marin County, ca. 1856 February 9 - 1861 November 1 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Mendocino County, 1858 April 23 - May 4 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Monterey County, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Napa County, 1853 July 21 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Nevada, 1861 April 20 - 1870 November 11 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Sacramento County, 1851 February 11 - 1869 March 27 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - San Francisco County (1 of 3), ca. 1847 July 13 - 1858 December 9 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - San Francisco County (2 of 3), ca. 1860 May 7 - 1868 June 18 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - San Francisco County (3 of 3), 1871 June 5 - 1877 August 6 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - San Mateo County, 1863 March 17 - 1869 December 28 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Santa Cruz County, 1864 October 22 - 1871 April 22 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Sierra County, 1867 July 9 - 1870 November 26 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Siskiyou County, 1854 February 9 - 1861 October 26 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Solano County, 1857 December 23 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Sonoma County, 1848 September 25 - 1849 December 10 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Texas, 1854 November 17 - 1858 November 27 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Trinity County, 1852 April 26 (Box 9, Folder 11)